Guide to the Jesse Gilbert Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Jesse Gilbert collection
1758-1867
MS 1739
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.25
(4 boxes)
The collection primarily consists of professional correspondence, deeds, land surveys, financial ledgers, a patent letter, receipts, promissory notes, proxy agreements, quit claims, and other materials that document the legal activities of Jesse Gilbert (1797) and other individuals who were possibly employed by the same New Haven law firm. The collection also contains a small amount of personal and family correspondence discussing family news and events.
Gilbert, Jesse, 1797-1851
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
The material is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
Scope and Contents
The collection primarily consists of professional correspondence, deeds, land surveys, financial ledgers, a patent letter, receipts, promissory notes, proxy agreements, quit claims, and other materials that document the legal activities of Jesse Gilbert (1797) and other individuals who were possibly employed by the same New Haven law firm. A significant portion of the collection, primarily the professional correspondence between Jesse Gilbert and E. W. Sturdevant, is devoted to a controversy over coal mining lands in the Wyoming Valley near Wilkes-Barre, Pennsylvania. Some of the professional correspondence relates to Gilbert's father, Jesse Gilbert (1762). The collection includes a few documents related to Timothy Dwight, Jeremiah Day, and Eli Whitney; a genealogy of the Thomas Smith family; and a voting record of the Hamden Council from the late eighteenth century. The collection also contains a small amount of personal and family correspondence discussing family news and events.
Biographical / Historical
Jesse Gilbert was born on December 30, 1797, to Jesse and Lydia B. Gilbert of Hamden, Connecticut. The oldest surviving son, Jesse had numerous siblings, including a brother, Griswold I. Gilbert, who was a member of the Connecticut State Senate in 1853. The Gilberts were a prominent family in New Haven; his great-great-grandfather was Matthew Gilbert, the first Deputy Governor of New Haven Colony, and his grandfather, Captain John Gilbert, was in command of New Haven's up-town militia during the Revolutionary War.
Gilbert married Laura Heaton on November 28, 1820. They had five children: Forbes Gilbert (b. 1821), Lydia, Street E., Howard D., and Jesse Burton. Gilbert was an attorney by profession, based out of New Haven, Connecticut, and had clients from throughout New England, Pennsylvania, and New York. Gilbert died on May 8, 1851.
Related Materials
Gilbert Family Papers. Hamden Historical Society.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jane Burton, 1999.
Real property; Lawyers; Gilbert family; Gilbert, Jesse, 1762-1833; Gilbert, Jesse, 1797-1851; Phelps, Oliver, 1749-1809; Sturdevant, Ebenezer Warren, b. 1806
- Act of Incorporation, Green Mountain Turnpike Company, Circa 1810-1830 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agreements
  - Billings, John and Albert, 1826 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bulkely, Jonathan, 1829 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Newbold, John, Undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence
  - Personal and Family
    - General, 1815 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Gilbert, Burton, 1863, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Gilbert, Forbes O., 1842-1848, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Gilbert, Griswold, 1833-1834 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Gilbert, Isaac, Griswold, and Augustus, 1836 June 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Gilbert, Jesse (1797), incoming, 1820-1821, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Gilbert, Laura, 1847 February 29 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Gilbert, Street E., 1845-1846, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Whitelaw, William, 1820 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Unknown, 1823 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Professional
    - General, 1800-1834, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Barnum, David, 1829 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Foote, Dr. Joseph, 1818-1820 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Gilbert, Jesse (1762), 1813, 1817 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Gilbert, Jesse (1797)
      - Incoming
        - General
          - A-D, 1833-1850 (Box 1, Folder 17)
            - Oversize, A, 1833 (Box 4, Folder 1)
          - L-S, 1845-1850, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
        - Sturdevant, E. W.
          - 1836-1837 (Box 1, Folder 19)
          - 1838-1839 (Box 1, Folder 20)
          - 1840-1849 (Box 1, Folder 21)
        - Unknown, Undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
      - Outgoing, 1813-1832 (Box 1, Folder 23)
        General
        Correspondence filed in this section are related to legal matters likely handled by Jesse Gilbert (1797), however it is possible some letters may be written by his father, Jesse Gilbert (1762).
        - Oversize, 1821 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Gilbert, Street E., 1867 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Hillhouse, William, 1803-1827 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Jefferds, Samuel, 1782-1820 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Kensett, Thomas, 1823-1824 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Mills, Isaac, 1816-1821 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Owen, Alfred, 1829-1830 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Phelps, Oliver
      - General, 1802-1805 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Smith, Cephas
        - Incoming, 1799-1805 (Box 2, Folder 2)
        - Outgoing, 1802, 1804 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Tallman, David, 1821-1830 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Deeds
  - 1767-1799 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Oversize, 1791 November 9 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - 1800-1832, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Oversize, 1807-1832, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Quit Claims, 1810-1833, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Oversize, 1832-1833 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- Genealogy, Smith Family, Undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Ledgers, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Maps and Surveys, 1795, 1830, 1833, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Oversize, 1830, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Patent Letter, 1810 July 26 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Promissory Notes, 1819-1831 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Proxy Agreements, 1767-1833 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Receipts
  - 1758, 1800-1819 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1820-1824 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 1825-1829 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 1830-1839, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Tax, 1788-1842, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Record of Votes, Hamden Council, Circa 1760-1780 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous, 1803, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)